Connecticut Central Railroad Records
© 2009 University of Connecticut
Connecticut Central Railroad Records.
undated, 1967-1998, 2008.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Connecticut Central Railroad.
3.0 linear feet.
MSS20090091
The collection consists of administrative files, photographs, and DVDs associated with the formation, maintenance and demise of the Connecticut Central Railroad, a freight line that ran in and around Middletown, Connecticut, from 1987 to 1998.
History
In 1986, Conrail filed for abandonment of trackage in and around Middletown, Connecticut. The Connecticut Department of Transportation purchased this so-called "Middletown Cluster" and named the Valley Railroad as designated operator. The Valley Railroad - an Essex, Connecticut-based tourist operator - had successfully negotiated an interchange agreement with Conrail and set up a subsidiary called the Connecticut Central Railroad to provide the service. The first train ran on May 26, 1987.
Connecticut Central Railroad (assigned alphanumeric code CCCL - 416) handled pulpboard, lumber, fertilizer, chemicals, and brick at above-projected levels until 1990 when its volume fell by one-third mostly due to the recession and closure of a major customer. That same year the Valley Railroad sold its interest to a group of investors and the CCCL became independent. The signing of a large sludge-hauling contract with the City of Middletown in 1990 plus the 1992 arrival of a large steel business enabled the CCCL to maintain a viable operation.
With a view to expansion, CCCL negotiated with the State of Connecticut for freight operation rights on the "Wethersfield Secondary" between the railroad’s northern end in Cromwell, Connecticut, and the Connecticut Southern Railroad’s Hartford, Connecticut, terminal. Shortly after these rights were awarded, the Providence and Worcester Railroad acquired the CCCL and began operations in April 1998.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of administrative files, photographs, and DVDs associated with the formation, operation and demise of the Connecticut Central Railroad, a freight line that ran in and around Middletown, Connecticut, from 1987 to 1998. Included in the collection are administrative files of day-to-day operations, employee timesheets, rate quotes, bills of laden, train operation manuals, financial documents, and notes written by company presidents James Goodwin and Russell St. John. Also in the collection are documents dealing with the creation and eventual sale of the company, proposed business plans, logo sketches, naming of officers, corporation set-up forms, and stock transfer agreements. The collection includes photographs of company employees, trains and equipment, derailments and break-ins, track surveys, and construction photos, as well as DVDs showing the building of railroad track, a video of one of the company’s locomotives appearing on the David Letterman Show as part of a sketch for a show on August 13, 1990, and of the swing bridge in Middletown, Connecticut, used in a 1993 music video of the Billy Joel song "River of Dreams."
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroad and Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Goodwin, James.; St. John, Russell.
Organizations:
Conrail.; Valley Railroad.; Essex Railroad.; Providence & Worcester Railroad.; Connecticut Central Railroad.
Places:
Middletown [Conn.]
Subjects:
Railroads--Connecticut.; Railroad companies--Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Maps.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Press releases.; Audio visual materials.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Drawings.; Contracts.; Sound recordings.; Bylaws.; Newspapers.; Advertisements.
Acquisition Information
The Connecticut Central Railroad Records were donated in August 2009 by Mr. James Goodwin and Mr. Russell St. John, former presidents of the company.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Administrative files, undated, 1967-1998, 2008
  - Thank you letter from a young boy to the company for giving his classmates a ride on the train, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Company letterhead stationery (blank), undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Company advertisement, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Computer directory tree, instructions for computer programs, undated, 1986-1987 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - To-do lists and notes, from James Goodwin, undated, 1986-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Rules and regulations for working with flagmen and outside contractors; pre-op ALCO S4 inspection procedures, undated, 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - CCCL operating manual and train handling practices, undated, 1994, 1996-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Photocopies of newspaper articles involving railroads in Portland and Middletown, Connecticut, 1967-1994 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Conrail application for the abandonment of the Middletown secondary track, 1985-1986 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Conrail property assessment of the Middletown Cluster, 1986 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Business plan for the operation of the Middletown Cluster, proposed budget and transportation consultant's observations, 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Proposal for the acquisition and operation of the Middletown Cluster, press releases and customer updates, 1986-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 12)
  - Conveyance documents -- Conrail's abandonment and negotiations between Conrail, CCCL, and the State of Connecticut, 1986-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
  - "Day One" documents of setting up the corporation -- bylaws, tax registration application, and certificate of incorporation, 1986-1987, 1990 (Box 2:, Folder 14)
  - Freight tariffs and rate quotes, 1986-1991 (Box 2:, Folder 15)
  - Sketch of a proposed CCCL logo, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 16)
  - Freight car loan agreement between CCCL and South Pacific Transport Company, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
  - Operating employee's timetables, 1987-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - CCCL taxes, budget, revenue and accountant information, 1987-1988 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Designation of officials, organizational chart, directory, Board of Director's meeting, and employee application form (blank), 1987-1989, 1993 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - Financial documents and rate tables, 1987-1996 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles about CCCL, 1987-1998 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - CCCL viability study for the operation of the Middletown-Hartford Corridor, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Documents related to the Rail Carrier Cost Recovery adjustment in freight rates, 1988-1990 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Documents related to the split of the Valley Railroad from CCCL, 1990 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Audited financial documents, 1997 (Box 3:, Folder 26)
  - Stock exchange agreement between CCCL and the Providence & Worcester Railroad, 1997 (Box 3:, Folder 27)
  - Acquisition and operation of CCCL by the Providence & Worcester Railroad, 1998 (Box 3:, Folder 28)
  - Train crew time reports, 1998 (Box 3:, Folder 29)
  - June 1998 issue of Railpace Newsmagazine with a tribute article about CCCL (Box 3:, Folder 30)
  - Ten-year reunion invitation to former CCCL employees, 2008 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
- Series II: Photographs and negatives, undated, 1980s-1990s
  - View of CCCL engine #35 from bridge into Middletown, Connecticut, undated (Box 4:, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbook of CCCL scenes, employees and equipment, undated (Box 4:, Folder 33)
  - Trucks and equipment, undated (Box 4:, Folder 34)
  - Loading of freight at the Diamond (intersecting track) and on the spur in the CCCL Middletown yard, undated (Box 4:, Folder 35)
  - Scenes of track on the "Wethersfield Secondary,", undated (Box 4:, Folder 36)
  - Views from Goldspur looking north and south, undated (Box 4:, Folder 37)
  - Swing bridge (a moveable railroad bridge between Middletown and Portland, Connecticut, on the track, which opened by pivoting on a center pier making a swinging action), undated (Box 4:, Folder 38)
  - Hi Rail on Airport Road in Hartford, Connecticut, undated (Box 4:, Folder 39)
  - Track construction, undated (Box 4:, Folder 40)
  - Around Middletown, Connecticut, undated (Box 4:, Folder 41)
  - Swing bridge fire, wheels, transport of construction equipment, undated, 1988 (Box 4:, Folder 42)
  - "Work-a-day" scenes, undated, 1988, 1995 (Box 4:, Folder 43)
  - Derailment, undated, 1990 (Box 4:, Folder 44)
  - First shipment for Primary Steel, undated, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 45)
  - Switching cars at the Middletown yard, 1980s (Box 4:, Folder 46)
  - Middletown yard and Portland freight house, 1980s (Box 4:, Folder 47)
  - James Goodwin "switching the stone container" (providing service to the Stone Container box factory in Portland, Connecticut, by delivering and/or picking up loaded and/or empty cars), 1987 (Box 4:, Folder 48)
  - Opening Day celebration, 1987 (Box 4:, Folder 49)
  - Locomotive roster shots, 1987-1998 (Box 4:, Folder 50)
  - Accidents, break-ins, derailments and damages, 1987-1995 (Box 5:, Folder 51)
  - Rockfall and Middlefield, Connecticut, 1988 (Box 5:, Folder 52)
  - Middlefield interchange construction, 1989 (Box 5:, Folder 53)
  - CCCL engines 35 and 36 at Reeds Gap (location of the Tilcon rock quarry on Route 68 in East Wallingford, Connecticut, near Durham, Connecticut), 1989, December 20 (Box 5:, Folder 54)
  - Operators and workers, 1989, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 55)
  - Derailment at Cedar Hill Yard in New Haven, Connecticut, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 56)
  - Locomotive "Roger Williams" at the Middletown, Connecticut, yard (the locomotive was owned by a private individual and was temporarily stored at the CCCL yard), 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 57)
  - Bridge inspection, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 58)
  - Track inspection survey, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 59)
  - Train #53 in Middlefield, Connecticut, with hopper and caboose, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 60)
  - Run to Pratt & Whitney Aircraft and Wayside, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 61)
  - Track maintenance, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 62)
  - Middletown/Cromwell expansion, 1990s (Box 5:, Folder 63)
  - Sludge train, 1990 (Box 5:, Folder 64)
  - Track survey, 1990 (Box 5:, Folder 65)
  - Evans Road bridge in Rocky Hill, Connecticut, before restoration, 1991 (Box 5:, Folder 66)
  - CCCL cars, 1992 (Box 5:, Folder 67)
  - Wheel change on engine 36, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 68)
  - Route 66 bridge and construction of a bridge over Washington Street in Middletown, Connecticut, 1995 (Box 5:, Folder 69)
  - Swing bridge turned by hand as crew waits in retired safety boat, 1995 (Box 5:, Folder 70)
  - Roster shots taken at Cedar Hill Yard in New Haven, Connecticut, 1995 (Box 5:, Folder 71)
  - Old New Haven Railroad freight station in Cromwell, Connecticut, 1995 August (Box 5:, Folder 72)
  - Photographic negatives of photographs in collection, undated (Box 5:, Folder 73)
  - Large prints of the swing bridge with CCCL president Russell St. John standing on side, CCCL employee Steve Loomis in the cab of an engine, and engine #36, 1990s (Box 6:, Folder 74)
- Series III: DVDs, undated, 1990, 1993-1994
  - "Airline Railroad, 10/31/94" [Part 1] -- video of the repair and construction of railroad track along the "Airline Railroad" in Connecticut, specifically the along the right-of-way belonging to the Connecticut Central Railroad near Middletown. Produced by West Street Productions, 1994; narrated by Russ Fowler (Box 6:, Folder 75)
  - "Airline Railroad, The Crossing, 1935" [Part 2] -- video of the construction of railroad track at West Street in Middletown, Connecticut, belonging to the Connecticut Central Railroad. Produced by West Street Productions, date unknown; narrated by Russ Fowler, undated (Box 6:, Folder 76)
  - "Airline Railroad, Shoofly 9/18/06" [Part 3] -- video of the construction of railroad track along the "Airline Railroad" in Connecticut, specifically the along the right-of-way on Route 66 in Middletown belonging to the Connecticut Central Railroad. Produced by West Street Productions, date unknown; narrated by Russ Fowler. Note from James Goodwin regarding the "Shoofly": "A Shoofly is a short-term detour installed near the main line while a bridge is under construction. It is removed as soon as the main project is completed. The bridge in question is that over Route 66 in Middletown, Connecticut. The project of removing the old railroad bridge and reopening the track on a new bridge took over a year so we needed a temporary bypass to keep our traffic moving. The track was rebuilt to cross Route 66 at grade level, which was a major inconvenience for everyone involved. The Shoofly was removed as soon as the new bridge was ready,", undated (Box 6:, Folder 77)
  - "Billy Joel, River of Dreams/David Letterman/Breaking [sic] Through" -- three seperate videos: 1) Braking Through, by Chris France, about the operation of the swing bridge used by CCCL in Middletown, Connecticut, undated; 2) "River of Dreams," a music video featuring singer Billy Joel, where he is shown standing on the swing bridge in Middletown, Connecticut, 1993; video of a sketch from the David Letterman Show of August 13, 1990, where a CCCL locomotive runs into objects set on the track's right-of-way, 1990, undated, 1990, 1993 (Box 6:, Folder 78)
  - Portion of the David Letterman Show of August 13, 1990, featuring a CCCL train that runs into objects set on the track's right-of-way. Includes "behind the scenes" footage (Box 6:, Folder 79)